{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This country’s classical music includes a suite with movements about the 1710 Siege of Viborg. This country’s national anthem, “Maamme,” [mahhm-may] ends that collection, the Karelia Suite, which was written by this country’s most prominent composer, Jean Sibelius. Sibelius’ most famous work is named for this country and protested Russian censorship of its early 20th century nationalism. For ten points, name this country where many of Sibelius’ works were premiered in Helsinki.",
      "answer": "Finland"
    },
    {
      "question": "Alexander Bliss preserved a copy of this speech that had been requested by George Bancroft. A two-hour oration by Edward Everett preceded this speech. The end of this speech claims that “government of the people, by the people, for the people, shall not perish from the earth.” The phrase “Fourscore and seven years ago” opens, for ten points, what Abraham Lincoln speech delivered after a Civil War battle?",
      "answer": "Gettysburg Address"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this country, Erich Hoenmanns sparked the Mechelen Incident after he crashed his plane, revealing a planned invasion called Case Yellow. This country was the target of the 18 Days” Campaign, which included a valiant but futile defense at the river Leie. The Force Publique, soldiers from this country’s colony the Congo, clashed with Italian soldiers in World War II. Leopold III led, for ten points, what country that surrendered to Germany after the fall of Brussels?",
      "answer": "Belgium"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this conflict, suspected collaborators were tortured in the Phoenix Program. The Siege of Khe Sanh took place in this conflict after it was widened following a phantom attack on the USS Maddox in the Gulf of Tonkin. American troops in this conflict were criticized for their use of Agent Orange. For ten points, name this unpopular Southeast Asian war that ended with the capture of Saigon.",
      "answer": "Vietnam War"
    },
    {
      "question": "A race riot in this state destroyed the neighborhood of Greenwood, which was known as “Black Wall Street.” The Red River of the South is the southern border of this state, whose capital was the target of the Timothy McVeigh bombing. The Trail of Tears took Native Americans to this state, which was then called “Indian Territory.” The “Sooners” settled, for ten points, what state directly north of Texas?",
      "answer": "Oklahoma"
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader’s premier was nearly blown up by a bomb on the Kashmir Princess while dispatched to the Bandung Conference. The Cultural Revolution was organized by this man to stop bourgeois infiltrators from restoring capitalism in his country. This man first came to prominence while leading the Long March to save his army from the Nationalists. The Little Red Book is a collection of sayings by, for ten points, what father of Communist China?",
      "answer": "Mao Zedong"
    },
    {
      "question": "24,000 tons of dynamite were detonated at once so that this project could utilize the Culebra Cut. This project, which was greatly expanded after a 2006 referendum approved the Third Lock project, was the subject of the Torrijos-Carter treaties. Theodore Roosevelt supported the construction of, for ten points, what Central American waterway that connects the Atlantic and Pacific Oceans?",
      "answer": "Panama Canal"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man expressed his desire that “poisonous envenomed worms” be drafted into forced labor, and demanded synagogues be burned to the ground in his On the Jews and their Lies. Frederick III kidnapped this man and held him in Wartburg Castle to protect him from the Holy Roman Emperor. In Exsurge Domine, Leo X threatened this man with excommunication if he didn’t recant his beliefs. For ten points, name this former German friar who created the 95 Theses.",
      "answer": "Martin Luther"
    },
    {
      "question": "John Singer Sargent created a portrait of this man “painting by the edge of a wood” with his wife Alice. This artist, who observed and painted the Rouen Cathedral under several different light conditions, built a garden-filled estate in Giverny [zhi-vair-nee] that is now a museum dedicated to him. Japanese-style bridges and water lilies were popular subjects of paintings by, for ten points, what French painter whose painting of a sunrise gave its name to the Impressionist movement?",
      "answer": "Claude Monet"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the aftermath of this battle, Benjamin Lincoln accepted the sword of Charles O’Hara. The losing side in this battle attempted to retreat to Gloucester Point. A British band at this battle may have started playing “The World Turned Upside Down.” A fleet under Comte de Rochambeau blocked reinforcements from this battle in the Battle of Chesapeake Bay. Charles Cornwallis was defeated at, for ten points, what 1781 battle, the final major clash of the American Revolution?",
      "answer": "Battle of Yorktown"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An obscene message opposing this policy was protected as free speech in Cohen v. California. In 1863, working-class men, resentful of wealthy people’s ability to pay a $300 fee to be exempt from this policy, started a riot in New York City. During the Vietnam War, this process was carried out by televised lottery. For ten points, name this policy of mandatory military service.",
        "answer": [
          "conscription",
          "the draft",
          "Selective Service"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This boxer refused to participate in the draft, saying that “war is against the teachings of the Qur’an.” In 1971, this man’s conviction for draft-dodging was overturned by the Supreme Court.",
        "answer": [
          "Muhammad Ali",
          "Cassius Clay"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The exile of Saad Zaghlul and his Wafd Party associates to Malta sparked this country’s 1919 revolution. A leader of this country was killed after ordering the arrest of the Coptic Pope. In this country, Farouk I was overthrown by the Free Officers Movement led by Muhammad Naguib. This country fought a brief war with France and Britain after its President nationalized the Suez Canal. For ten points, name this country where Anwar Sadat was assassinated in Cairo.",
        "answer": "Egypt"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The nationalization of the Suez Canal was carried out by this man, who forced Muhammad Naguib to step down in 1954.",
        "answer": "Gamal Abdel Nasser"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man executed thousands of prisoners after launching the Night Attack on Targovishite. Matthias Corvinus imprisoned this man after he asked for help against Mehmed II. This man was engaged in a power struggle with Vladislav II, who was backed by John Hunyadi. This man became Voivode of Wallachia after the death of his father. For ten points, name this Romanian ruler named for his habit of putting his enemies on stakes.",
        "answer": [
          "Vlad III Dracul",
          "Vlad the Imapler"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Diary of a Young Girl is an abridged version of a diary written by Anne Frank who recorded her experiences living in Gies’s Achterhuis [ak-ter-house] in this city.",
        "answer": "Amsterdam"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This thinker’s namesake school of thought was expanded by the critical theorists of the Frankfurt School. This thinker argued that the exploitation of labor was the source of profit and coined the term “commodity fetishism.” This man’s most famous work opens with the phrase “a spectre is haunting Europe,” and was co-written with Friedrich Engels. For ten points, name this author of Das Kapital and the Communist Manifesto.",
        "answer": "Karl Marx"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Marx and Engels published the Communist Manifesto in this year, in which it helped inspire people in minor uprisings in Germany; it did not spread quickly enough to inspire the broader uprisings of this year’s “Spring of Nations.”",
        "answer": "1848"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man ordered the execution of Cuauht´emoc while en route to remove his rival Crist´obal de Olid at Triunfo de la Cruz. After being told to return from his expedition by the governor of Cuba, this man burned his own ships. La Malinche served as a translator for this man, who commanded European and Tlaxcala forces at the Battle of Otumba. Tenochtitlan was burned by, for ten points, what Spanish conquistador who destroyed the Aztec Empire?",
        "answer": "Hernan Cortes"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During his conquest, Hernan Cortes overthrew this last Aztec Emperor.",
        "answer": [
          "Moctezuma II",
          "Montezuma II"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1636, conflict over control of this resource in the Connecticut River Valley led to the Pequot War. French-Canadian traders, known as Coureurs des bois, traveled the woods exchanging European goods for this resource. In the early 19th century, John Jacob Astor founded a company dealing in this commodity to counter the Hudson’s Bay Company’s monopoly. For ten points, name this commodity often acquired from beaver pelts.",
        "answer": [
          "fur",
          "pelts before it is read"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Pequot War was ended by a treaty signed in this capital of Connecticut.",
        "answer": "Hartford"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This element, which is today stored in its “hex” or hexafluoride form, was used in Enrico Fermi’s Chicago Pile-1. Martin Klaproth discovered this element in pitchblende, which can be processed into yellowcake. This element, which alpha decays into thorium, is most commonly found in a 238 isotope, and its 235 isotope is enriched for nuclear fuel. For ten points, name this radioactive element named for the seventh planet from the sun, with symbol U.",
        "answer": [
          "uranium",
          "U before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Unlike Little Boy, which used uranium, the Fat Man bomb used against Nagasaki used this other element as fuel. It has an atomic number 94 and symbol Pu.",
        "answer": "plutonium"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Early Virginia",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "First President of the United States, who retired to Mount Vernon.",
          "answer": "George Washington"
        },
        {
          "question": "City that was made its capital in 1780.",
          "answer": "Richmond"
        },
        {
          "question": "Cash crop cultivated by John Rolfe that sustained the colony.",
          "answer": "tobacco"
        },
        {
          "question": "Legislative body that governed the colony until it was changed to the House of Delegates.",
          "answer": "House of Burgesses"
        },
        {
          "question": "Politician who exclaimed “give me liberty or give me death.”",
          "answer": "Patrick Henry"
        },
        {
          "question": "Home of Thomas Jefferson located outside Charlottesville.",
          "answer": "Monticello"
        },
        {
          "question": "City that was founded as Middle Plantation and was capital from 1699 to 1780.",
          "answer": "Williamsburg"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ninth governor of Virginia, a member of the illustrious Lee family, who earned his nickname as a cavalry commander.",
          "answer": [
            "Henry “Light-Horse Harry” Lee III",
            "Harry Lee"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Russian Federation",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Russian capital city that has expanded past its Third Ring Road.",
          "answer": "Moscow"
        },
        {
          "question": "Former Communist superpower, in which it was the largest member.",
          "answer": [
            "Soviet Union",
            "USSR",
            "Union of Soviet Socialist Republics",
            "CCCP",
            "Soyuz Sovetskikh Sotsialisticheskikh Respublik"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Politician who served as Prime Minister for four years in between his first and current terms as President.",
          "answer": "Vladimir Putin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country from which it seized Sevastopol in 2014.",
          "answer": "Ukraine"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who succeeded Mikhail Gorbachev as first President of post-1991 Russia.",
          "answer": "Boris Yeltsin"
        },
        {
          "question": "President who oversaw the Russo-Georgian War in 2008.",
          "answer": "Dmitry Medvedev"
        },
        {
          "question": "Region containing Grozny that has fought Russia for independence.",
          "answer": "Chechnya"
        },
        {
          "question": "Month in which a coup against Gorbachev resulted in the creation of the Russian Federation.",
          "answer": "August Coup"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Canada",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "City selected by Queen Victoria to be Canada’s capital in 1857.",
          "answer": "Ottawa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Federal police force known for its bright red uniforms.",
          "answer": [
            "Royal Canadian Mounted Police",
            "RCMP",
            "Mounties"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "French speaking province that was the site of the October Crisis.",
          "answer": "Quebec"
        },
        {
          "question": "City in Nova Scotia where a 1917 explosion killed 2,000 people.",
          "answer": "Halifax"
        },
        {
          "question": "Award won by Lester Pearson for mediating the Suez Crisis.",
          "answer": "Nobel Peace Prize"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prime Minister who dealt with the October Crisis in 1970.",
          "answer": "Pierre Trudeau"
        },
        {
          "question": "1869 rebellion led by Louis Riel in what is now Manitoba.",
          "answer": "Red River Rebellion"
        },
        {
          "question": "Longest-serving Prime Minister, who led Canada through World War II.",
          "answer": "William Lyon Mackenzie King"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1904, this person sued fifty-five newspapers for libel after they followed William Randolph Hearst in reporting that she had been arrested for stealing to support a cocaine addiction. This performer, nicknamed Watanya Cicilla, volunteered a company of fifty (20 pts)",
        "female soldiers for the Spanish-American War, but was ignored. While working with (10 pts)",
        "Sitting Bull, this performer was nicknamed “Little Sure Shot” on posters advertising Buffalo Bill’s Wild West Show. For ten points, name this incredible American female sharpshooter."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Annie Oakley",
        "Annie Oakley Butler",
        "Phoebe Ann Mosey"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A president of this nation, Abdal´a Bucaram, was once an Olympic-caliber hurdler and became known as “El Loco” during his tenure. This nation’s most recent election brought the wheelchair-bound Lenin (20 pts)",
        "Moreno to power, succeeding his mentor Rafael Correa. Moreno allowed Scotland Yard to enter this nation’s (10 pts)",
        "embassy in London in 2019 to arrest the founder of WikiLeaks. For ten points, name this country that protected Julian Assange and has capital Quito."
      ],
      "answer": "Ecuador"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Due to its tenuous attribution to the Apostle John, this book was not accepted into the Armenian canon until about 1200 AD. In this book, a golden censer filled with coals is thrown onto the Earth and (20 pts)",
        "seven trumpets are blown to announce the arrival of plagues. A vision of the Whore of Babylon appears in this book, which features the (10 pts)",
        "return of Jesus and the defeat of Satan. For ten points, name this book by John of Patmos that depicts the end of the world, the last book of the New Testament."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Book of Revelation or the Apocalypse of John",
        "or The Revelation to John",
        "or The Revelation of Jesus Christ"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The entrance of one of these structures was graffitied in honor of Frederick Wilhelm IV by Karl Lepsius, who composed a list of these structures after visiting (20 pts)",
        "Dahshur. One of these structures, carved from white limestome and featuring six mastabas stacked upon each other, was designed for (10 pts)",
        "Djoser by Imhotep. Despite their common use as tombs, there are none of these structures in the Valley of the Kings. Khufu, Menkaure, and Khafre commissioned, for ten points, what common tomb for Pharaohs, three of which are at Giza?"
      ],
      "answer": "pyramids"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Operation RYAN was conducted by this agency. Robert Hanssen received 15 life sentences for collaborating with this agency, whose predecessors included the NKVD. A group of British recruits who became known as the (20 pts)",
        "Cambridge Five worked with this organization. A member of this organization named Rudolf Abel was (10 pts)",
        "exchanged for downed U2 pilot Gary Powers. Vladimir Putin once served as an officer in, for ten points, what Soviet intelligence agency?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "KGB or Komitet gosudarstvennoy bezopasnosti",
        "or the Committee for State Security"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Michael Jordan played for this team’s AA affiliate, the Birmingham Barons, during his first retirement from basketball. Steve Dahl promoted and executed “Disco Demolition Night” at this team’s (20 pts)",
        "Comiskey Park in 1979. Multiple members of this team, including Buck Weaver and Shoeless Joe Jackson, were (10 pts)",
        "accused of taking bribes to throw the 1919 World Series, after which it took until 2005 to win another World Series. For ten points, name this baseball team that experienced the “Black Sox” scandal."
      ],
      "answer": "Chicago White Sox"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Husband Kimmel was found in “dereliction of duty” for his actions during this event and demoted two full ranks. In the aftermath of this event, its planner legendarily worried that he had awoken a (20 pts)",
        "“sleeping giant.” Franklin Roosevelt called this event a (10 pts)",
        "“day that shall live in infamy” in a speech to Congress that prompted the declaration of war against Japan. For ten points, name this December 7th, 1941 surprise attack on a base in Hawaii that brought the United States into World War II."
      ],
      "answer": "attack on Pearl Harbor"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Alexandre Gonsse de Rougeville attempted to save this monarch in the Carnation Plot. This royal’s signature was forged in an attempt to sell expensive jewelry in the (20 pts)",
        "Affair of the Diamond Necklace. The Petit Trianon, originally designed for Madame de Pompadour, was given to this woman. This woman was forced to flee to (10 pts)",
        "Tuileries Palace under the watch of the Marquis de Lafayette after a crowd seized Versailles. For ten points, name this wife of Louis XVI who legendarily said “Let them eat cake” during the French Revolution."
      ],
      "answer": "Marie Antoinette"
    }
  ]
}